A Guide to the Southampton County (Va.) Judgments, 1743-1943
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Southampton County (Va.) Judgments, 1743-1943
Library of Virginia
1050775-1050778, 1119643-1119694, 1147497-1147639
90 cu. ft. (168 boxes)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
These items came in a transfer of court papers from Southampton County.
Historical Information
Southampton County was formed from Isle of Wight County in 1749. A part of Nansemond County was added in 1785.
The County Court was the original colonial court of adjudication and recordation, and it was the principal tribunal for the administration of local justice. The individual justices could act on small claims matters as well as criminal matters where imminent bodily harm was a possibility, there being an appeal to the full County Court, which met monthly. This court ceased to exist in 1904 and the recordation function was transferred to the circuit court.
The District Courts were created by the General Assembly in 1788. They were designed to alleviate congestion in the General Court which had caused long delays in adjudication of common law cases. The District Courts were abolished in 1808 and were replaced by the superior courts of law.
The Superior Court of Law was created in 1808. It met twice a year in each county, presided over by a circuit-riding General Court judge. Records were filed with the County Court. It had civil and criminal jurisdiction. The court ceased to exist in 1831.
The Circuit Superior Courts of Law and Chancery, established in 1831, were the upper courts on the local level. Sessions were held twice a year in each county, presided over by a General Court judge. The counties were grouped into districts for the convenience of the judge. The court ceased to exist in 1851.
The Circuit Court was authorized by the Constitution of 1851 and established by an act of the General Assembly passed in May 1852. Courts were held twice yearly in each county, presided over by 21 judges who rode circuits in the area of their jurisdiction. The records were filed with County Court records. These courts were granted original jurisdiction concurrrent with that of the County Courts, as well as appellate jurisdiction in all civil cases of more than fifty dollars and criminal cases not "expressly cognizable in some other court," including those involving loss of life.
Scope and Content
Southampton County (Va.) Judgments, 1743-1943, contain civil cases heard in County Court, District Court, Superior Court of Law, Circuit Superior Court, and Circuit Court in which justice was administered on the strictly formulated rules of common law. The majority of cases in this record series relate to matters of debt. A few boxes in the collection contain additional material such as clerks' notes, letters, and criminal warrants.
Arrangement
Chronological (Cases filed within each box by month and year they were resolved.)
Access Terms
Southampton County (Va.) -- Circuit Court.; Southampton County (Va.) -- Circuit Superior Court of Law and Chancery.; Southampton County (Va.) -- County Court.; Southampton County (Va.) -- District Court.; Southampton County (Va.) -- Superior Court of Law.; Civil procedure -- Virginia -- Southampton County.; Courts -- Virginia -- Southampton County.; Debt -- Virginia -- Southampton County.; Judgments -- Virginia -- Southampton County.; Public Records -- Virginia -- Southampton County.; Southampton County (Va.) -- History.; Judicial records -- Virginia -- Southampton County.; Local government records -- Virginia -- Southampton County.
Contents List
- Judgments, County Court 1743-1751 (Barcode 1147497)
- Judgments, County Court (Oversize) 1752-1821 (Barcode 1119646)
- Judgments, County Court 1752-1754 (Barcode 1147498)
- Judgments, County Court 1754-1755 (Barcode 1147499)
- Judgments, County Court 1755-1756 (Barcode 1147500)
- Judgments, County Court 1756-1758 (Barcode 1147501)
- Judgments, County Court 1758-1759 (Barcode 1147502)
- Judgments, County Court 1760-1761 (Barcode 1147503)
- Judgments, County Court 1761-1762 (Barcode 1147504)
- Judgments, County Court 1763 (Barcode 1147505)
- Judgments, County Court 1764 (Barcode 1147506)
- Judgments, County Court 1764-1765 (Barcode 1147507)
- Judgments, County Court 1765-1766 (Barcode 1147508)
- Judgments, County Court 1766-1767 (Barcode 1147509)
- Judgments, County Court 1767 (Barcode 1147510)
- Judgments, County Court 1767-1768 (Barcode 1147511)
- Judgments, County Court 1768-1769 (Barcode 1147512)
- Judgments, County Court 1770-1771 (Barcode 1147513)
- Judgments, County Court 1771-1772 (Barcode 1147514)
- Judgments, County Court 1772-1773 (Barcode 1147515)
- Judgments, County Court 1773-1775 (Barcode 1147516)
- Judgments, County Court 1776-1783 (Barcode 1147517)
- Judgments, County Court 1783-1784 (Barcode 1147518)
- Judgments, County Court 1784 (Barcode 1147519)
- Judgments, County Court 1784-1785 (Barcode 1147520)
- Judgments, County Court 1785-1786 (Barcode 1147521)
- Judgments, County Court 1786-1787 (Barcode 1147522)
- Judgments, County Court 1787-1788 (Barcode 1147523)
- Judgments, County Court 1788-1789 (Barcode 1147524)
- Judgments, County Court 1789-1790 (Barcode 1147527)
- Judgments, County Court 1790-1791 (Barcode 1147528)
- Judgments, County Court 1791 (Barcode 1147529)
- Judgments, County Court 1791-1792 (Barcode 1147530)
- Judgments, District Court and Superior Courts 1793-1826 (Barcode 1119643)
- Judgments, County Court 1793 (Barcode 1147531)
- Judgments, County Court 1794-1795 (Barcode 1147532)
- Judgments, County Court 1795 (Barcode 1147533)
- Judgments, County Court 1795-1796 (Barcode 1147534)
- Judgments, County Court 1796-1797 (Barcode 1147535)
- Judgments, County Court 1797-1798 (Barcode 1147536)
- Judgments, County Court 1798-1799 (Barcode 1147537)
- Judgments, County Court 1799-1800 (Barcode 1147538)
- Judgments, County Court 1800 (Barcode 1147539)
- Judgments, County Court 1801 (Barcode 1147540)
- Judgments, County Court 1801 (Barcode 1147541)
- Judgments, County Court 1802 (Barcode 1147542)
- Judgments, County Court 1802-1803 (Barcode 1147543)
- Judgments, County Court 1803-1804 (Barcode 1147544)
- Judgments, County Court 1804-1805 (Barcode 1147545)
- Judgments, County Court 1805 (Barcode 1147546)
- Judgments, County Court 1805 (Barcode 1147547)
- Judgments, County Court 1806 (Barcode 1147548)
- Judgments, County Court 1806-1807 (Barcode 1147549)
- Judgments, County Court 1807 (Barcode 1147550)
- Judgments, County Court 1807-1808 (Barcode 1147551)
- Judgments, County Court 1808 (Barcode 1147552)
- Judgments, County Court 1809-1810 (Barcode 1147553)
- Judgments 1809-1816 (Barcode 1119649)
- Judgments, County Court 1810 (Barcode 1147554)
- Judgments, County Court 1810-1811 (Barcode 1147555)
- Judgments, County Court 1812-1813 (Barcode 1147556)
- Judgments, County Court 1813-1814 (Barcode 1147557)
- Judgments, County Court 1814-1815 (Barcode 1147558)
- Judgments, County Court 1816 (Barcode 1147559)
- Judgments, County Court 1816-1817 (Barcode 1147561)
- Judgments, County Court 1817 (Barcode 1147560)
- Judgments 1817-1819 (Barcode 1119650)
- Judgments, County Court 1818 (Barcode 1147562)
- Judgments, County Court 1818 (Barcode 1147563)
- Judgments, County Court 1818-1819 (Barcode 1147564)
- Judgments, County Court 1819-1820 (Barcode 1147565)
- Judgments, County Court 1820 (Barcode 1147566)
- Judgments, County Court 1820-1821 (Barcode 1147567)
- Judgments 1820-1821 (Barcode 1119651)
- Judgments 1821-1823 (Barcode 1119652)
- Judgments, County Court 1821 (Barcode 1147568)
- Judgments, County Court 1821-1822 (Barcode 1147569)
- Judgments, County Court 1822 (Barcode 1147570)
- Judgments, County Court 1823 (Barcode 1147571)
- Judgments, County Court 1823-1824 (Barcode 1147572)
- Judgments, County Court 1824 (Barcode 1147573)
- Judgments, County Court 1824-1825 (Barcode 1147574)
- Judgments 1824-1825 (Barcode 1119654)
- Judgments, County Court 1825 (Barcode 1147575)
- Judgments, County Court 1825-1826 (Barcode 1147576)
- Judgments, County Court 1826 (Barcode 1147577)
- Judgments 1826-1827 (Barcode 1119653)
- Judgments, County Court 1827 (Barcode 1147578)
- Judgments, County Court 1827 (Barcode 1147579)
- Judgments, County Court 1827 (Barcode 1147580)
- Judgments, County Court 1827 (Barcode 1147581)
- Judgments, County Court 1828 (Barcode 1147583)
- Judgments, County Court 1828 (Barcode 1147584)
- Judgments, County Court 1828 (Barcode 1147585)
- Judgments, County Court 1828 (Barcode 1147582)
- Judgments 1828-1829 (Barcode 1119656)
- Judgments 1829-1831 (Barcode 1119655)
- Judgments, County Court 1829 (Barcode 1147586)
- Judgments, County Court 1829 (Barcode 1147587)
- Judgments, County Court 1830 (Barcode 1147588)
- Judgments, County Court 1830 (Barcode 1147589)
- Judgments, County Court 1830 (Barcode 1147590)
- Judgments, County Court 1831 (Barcode 1147591)
- Judgments, County Court 1831 (Barcode 1147592)
- Judgments, County Court 1831-1832 (Barcode 1147593)
- Judgments 1831-1833 (Barcode 1119658)
- Judgments, County Court 1832 (Barcode 1147594)
- Judgments, County Court 1832-1833 (Barcode 1147595)
- Judgments, County Court 1833-1834 (Barcode 1147596)
- Judgments, County Court 1834 (Barcode 1147597)
- Judgments 1834-1835 (Barcode 1119657)
- Judgments, County Court 1835 (Barcode 1147598)
- Judgments, County Court 1836 (Barcode 1147599)
- Judgments 1836-1838 (Barcode 1119659)
- Judgments, County Court 1837 (Barcode 1147600)
- Judgments, County Court 1838 (Barcode 1147601)
- Judgments, County Court 1839 (Barcode 1147602)
- Judgments 1839-1841 (D) (Barcode 1119660)
- Judgments, County Court 1840 (Barcode 1147603)
- Judgments, County Court 1840-1841 (Barcode 1147604)
- Judgments, County Court 1841 (Barcode 1147605)
- Judgments 1841 (F)-1842 (C) (Barcode 1119661)
- Judgments 1842 (D)-1843 (H) (Barcode 1119662)
- Judgments, County Court 1842 (Barcode 1147606)
- Judgments, County Court 1842-1843 (Barcode 1147607)
- Judgments, County Court 1843 (Barcode 1147608)
- Judgments 1843 (J)-1844 (F) (Barcode 1119664)
- Judgments 1844 (G)-1846 (C) (Barcode 1119663)
- Judgments, County Court 1844 (Barcode 1147609)
- Judgments, County Court 1845-1846 (Barcode 1147610)
- Judgments 1846 (D)-1849 (N) (Barcode 1119665)
- Judgments, County Court 1847-1848 (Barcode 1147611)
- Judgments, County Court 1849-1850 (Barcode 1147612)
- Judgments 1849 (P)-1851 (Barcode 1119666)
- Judgments 1851-1857 (Barcode 1119669)
- Judgments, County Court 1851-1854 (Barcode 1147613)
- Judgments, County Court 1855-1857 (Barcode 1147614)
- Judgments, County Court 1858 (Barcode 1147615)
- Judgments 1858-1870 (Barcode 1119670)
- Judgments, County Court 1859-1860 (Barcode 1147616)
- Judgments, County Court 1861-1867 (Barcode 1147617)
- Judgments, County Court 1868 (Barcode 1147618)
- Judgments, County Court 1868-1870 (Barcode 1147619)
- Judgments, County Court 1870-1871 (Barcode 1147620)
- Judgments 1871-1884, 1893-1907 (Barcode 1119672)
- Judgments, County Court 1872 (Barcode 1147621)
- Judgments, County Court 1872-1873 (Barcode 1147622)
- Judgments, County Court 1874-1876 (Barcode 1147623)
- Judgments, County Court 1876-1878 (Barcode 1147624)
- Judgments, County Court 1879-1881 (Barcode 1147625)
- Judgments, County Court 1882-1883 (Barcode 1147626)
- Judgments, County Court 1884 (Barcode 1147627)
- Judgments, County Court 1885 (Barcode 1147628)
- Judgments, County Court 1886 (Barcode 1147629)
- Judgments, County Court 1887-1888 (Barcode 1147630)
- Judgments, County Court 1888-1889 (Barcode 1147631)
- Judgments, County Court 1890 (Barcode 1147632)
- Judgments, County Court 1891-1892 (Barcode 1147633)
- Judgments, County Court 1892-1893 (Barcode 1147634)
- Judgments, County Court 1894 (Barcode 1147635)
- Judgments, County Court 1894-1895 (Barcode 1147636)
- judgments, clerk's notes, letters, 1894-1907, 1924, 1930 (Barcode 1050776)
- Judgments, County Court 1896-1900 (Barcode 1147637)
- criminal warrants and judgments 1897-1911, 1940-1943 (Barcode 1050781)
- Judgments, County Court 1901-1903 (Barcode 1147638)
- Judgments 1908-1912 (Barcode 1119694)
- judgments 1913-1919, 1926 (Barcode 1050775)
- judgments 1920-1921, 1925, 1928 (Barcode 1050777)
- judgments 1920s-1930s (Barcode 1050778)
- Judgments, County Court n.d. (Barcode 1147639)